Finding Aid for Warren Lounsbury Smith papers, 1940-1972.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Warren Lounsbury Smith papers 1940-1972
Smith, Warren Lounsbury, 1914-1972.
8640 Aa 2
Professor of economics at University of Michigan, member of the President's Council of Economic Advisors, 1968-1969. Professional files, manuscripts of writings, notebooks of lecture notes, and other materials relating to the Council of Economic Advisors; and photographs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
13 linear feet
The collection was donated by Ann Smith Fowler (donor no. 5324 ) in 1975. Additional materials were received.
The collection is open to research.
Warren L. Smith was born in Watertown, New York, on March 23, 1914. He enrolled at the University of Michigan in 1940, but his studies were interrupted by service in the U.S. Army during World War II. He resumed his education at the University in 1946, receiving his B.A. in 1947, M.A. in 1949, and Ph.D. in economics in 1952. He taught for a time at the University of Virginia (1953-1956) and Ohio State University (1956-1957) before returning to the University of Michigan as an associate professor of economics. He was made full professor in 1959, and from 1963 to 1969, he served as chairman of the economics department. Smith was a prolific writer and conference speaker. In addition, he was an economics consultant to such government bodies as the Joint Economic Committee of the U.S. Congress (1959-1960), the Commission on Money and Credit (1960-1961), the Anti-Trust Division of the Justice Department (1961-1963), and the U.S. Department of the Treasury. Perhaps of greatest importance, Smith was a consultant to the President's Council of Economic Advisers (1961-1967), and served as a member of the Council from 1968 to 1969. Warren L. Smith died unexpectedly of a stroke on April 23, 1972.
The Smith papers consist of professional files, manuscripts of writings, notebooks of lecture notes, and other materials relating to the Council of Economic Advisors; and photographs. The papers are organized in ten series of material covering the period of his education and professional career, approximately 1940-1972. These series are: Personal / Biographical; Student notebooks and papers, 1940-1952; Teaching Materials; Printed writings; Unpublished papers; Student files; Correspondence; Papers and Conferences, circa 1952-1972; Council of Economic Advisors, 1961-1969; and Committees, conferences, and study groups.
Subjects:
Council of Economic Advisers (U.S.); Smith, Warren Lounsbury, 1914-1972.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Economics.; University of Michigan--Faculty.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Children--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Knight School (Scio, Mich.); Mack School (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Schools--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Smith, Warren Lounsbury, 1914-1972.; Students--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Personal / Biographical
  - Vitae, biographical sketches (Box 1)
  - Newspaper clippings (Box 1)
  - Public school report cards 1926-1928 address book, circa 1950-1960 (Box 1)
- Student notebooks and papers 1940-1952
  - Economics 52 (Box 1)
  - Economics 101 (Money and Credit) (Box 1)
  - Economics 105 (International Finance) (Box 1)
  - Economics 106 (Monetary Theory and Management) (Box 1)
  - Economics 121 (Labor) (Box 1)
  - Economics 131 (Corporations) (Box 1)
  - Economics 132 (Industrial Competition and Monopoly) (Box 1)
  - Economics 141 (International Trade) (Box 1)
  - Economics 142 (International Economic Policies) (Box 1)
  - Economics 143 (International Economics: Europe) (Box 1)
  - Economics 151 (Level of National Income and Employment) (Box 1)
  - Economics 152 (Prices and Economic Organization) (Box 1)
  - Economics 163 (American Economic Development) (Box 1)
  - Economics 163 ("Factors in the Location of Iron and Steel Works in the U.S.") (Box 1)
  - Economics 175 (Statistics), 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Economics 176 (Applications of Economic Statistics) (Box 1)
  - Economics 181 (Public Finance) (Box 1)
  - Economics 195 (The Location of Economic Activity (Box 1)
  - Economics 199 ("Marginal Productivity as a Determinant of Wages") (Box 1)
  - Economics 254 (Introduction to Mathematical Economics) (Box 1)
  - Economics 254 (Mathematical Economics) (Box 1)
  - Economics 255 (History of Economic Thought, I) (Box 1)
  - Economics 255 ("The Political Economy of Simonde De Sismondi") (Box 1)
  - Economics 256 (History of Economic Thought, II) (Box 1)
  - Economics 256 ("The Economics of John Bates Clark") (Box 2)
  - Economics 259 (Theories of Distribution) (Box 2)
  - Economics 301 and 302 (Seminar in Monetary and Banking Theory) (Box 2)
  - Economics 301 and 302 ("Monetary Theory and Keynesian Economics") (Box 2)
  - History (Recent History) (Box 2)
  - Mathematics 14 (Box 2)
  - Mathematics 127 (Theory of Statistics, I) (Box 2)
  - Mathematics 129 (Mathematical Theory of Probability) (Box 2)
  - Mathematics 151 (Advanced Calculus) (Box 2)
  - Philosophy 34 (Box 2)
  - Philosophy 34 (Box 2)
  - Political Science 92 (National Politics) (Box 2)
  - Unidentified notebooks
    - Economics (Box 2)
    - Philosophy (Box 2)
  - Economics syllabi
    - First semester 1941-1942 (Box 2)
    - Second semester 1941-1942 (Box 2)
  - Exams taken by the WLS
    - Economics (Box 2)
    - French, German, History, and Math (Box 2)
- Teaching Materials 1953-1972
  - Lecture notes (courses taught by WLS), ca. 1953-1972
    - Economics 51 (Box 2)
    - Economics 52 (Box 2)
    - Economics 100-A (Box 3)
    - Economics 101 and 102 (Box 3)
    - Economics 104, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Economics 126 (Box 3)
    - Economics 152 (Box 3)
    - Economics 175 (Box 3)
    - Economics 176 (Box 3)
    - Economics 206 (Box 3)
    - Economics 254 (Box 3)
    - Economics 257 (Box 3)
    - Economics 451 (Box 3)
    - Economics 611, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Economics 612, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Economics 615, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Economics 652 (Box 4)
    - Economics 751 (Box 4)
    - Economics miscellaneous, 6 folders (Box 4)
  - Course Evaluations of WLS courses: Economics 611, 615, and miscellaneous (Box 4)
  - Course Notes
    - Economics 175 (Box 4)
    - Economics 176 (Box 4)
    - Economics 201, 202, 206 (Box 5)
    - Economics 206 (Box 5)
    - Economics 301 and 302 (Box 5)
    - Economics 451 (Box 5)
    - Economics 611, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Economics 615 (Box 5)
    - Economics 652 (Box 5)
    - Economics 712 (Box 5)
    - Economics ("Money and Banking") (Box 5)
    - Economics ("Theories of Distribution") (Box 5)
  - Examinations
    - Economics 51 and 53 (Box 5)
    - Economics 101, 102, 125, 151, 201, 202, 205, 451, 751 (Box 5)
    - Economics 611 and 612 (Box 5)
    - Economics 612 (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous 1954-1955 (Box 5)
    - Preliminary Ph.D. exams (Box 5)
  - Course outlines (Box 5)
  - Reading lists
    - Economics 610 and 611 (Box 5)
    - Economics 612 (Box 5)
    - Economics 615 (Box 5)
    - Economics 652 (Box 5)
    - Economics miscellaneous (Box 5)
  - Economics bibliography and sources (Box 6)
  - Economics bibliographies and book lists (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous notes, 6 folders (Box 6)
  - Topical files circa 1950-1972
    - Analysis of Free Reserves (Box 6)
    - Bank Credit Expansion (Box 6)
    - Bank Portfolio Management (Box 6)
    - Business Cycle Model (Box 6)
    - Economics Society of Michigan (Box 6)
    - Exchange Depreciation and Income Effects (Box 6)
    - Factors Affecting Bank Reserves and Money Supply (Box 6)
    - Faculty Reform Coalition, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Federal Credit Programs (Box 6)
    - Forecasting and Fiscal Policy (Box 6)
    - General Theory and International Adjustments (Box 6)
    - Harvard University, Visiting Lecturer 1958-1959 (Box 6)
    - Inflation Models (Box 6)
    - Input-Output Analysis (Box 6)
    - International Liquidity (Box 6)
    - International Monetary Reform (Box 6)
    - International Monetary System: Miscellaneous papers (Box 6)
    - Joint Economic Committee, memoranda on Hearings 1959 (Box 6)
    - Long-Run Monetary Strategy (Box 6)
    - Money Wages and Employment (Box 6)
    - National Economics Club (Box 6)
    - Reserve Requirements in the American Monetary System (Box 7)
    - Selection of University Presidents (Box 7)
    - Tax Policy for Economic Stability and Growth (Box 7)
    - Treasury Transfers and Transit Clearings (Box 7)
    - University of Michigan, minutes, LSA faculty meetings miscellaneous material (Box 7)
    - University of Virginia, Charlottesville, miscellaneous correspondence (Box 7)
    - Urban Development Bank (Box 7)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 7)
- Printed writings 1954-1970
  - Articles
    - 1954-1959 (Box 7)
    - 1960-1970 (Box 7)
  - Reviews
    - 1957-1970 Drafts (Box 7)
  - Texts (Box 7)
  - Money and Banking, chapters 20, 10, 12 (Box 7)
    (rough drafts, probably unpublished)
- Unpublished papers (include writings of others)
  - "On Announcement. Effects in Monetary Policy" (Box 7)
  - "Discussion of Interest Rates and Portfolio Selection Among Liquid Assets," by Carl F. Christ (Box 7)
  - "Are Credit Developments in 1964 Cause for Concern?" (Box 7)
  - "Financial Intermediaries and Monetary Controls" (Box 7)
  - "Interest and Money in Macrodynamic Models" (Box 7)
  - "Population Growth and Maintenance of Full Employment" (Box 7)
- Student files
  - Dissertations and theses
    - Sm. Brant Gupta (Box 7)
    - Ralph Cowan (Box 7)
    - Harry Hutchinson (Box 7)
    - David Kain, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Benedict J. Pediotti (Box 7)
    - Gail Pierson (Box 7)
    - Martha Seger (Box 7)
    - Paul Smith (Box 7)
  - Letters of recommendation (Box 7)
- Correspondence
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, 10 folders (Box 8)
  - Personal correspondence (Box 8)
  - Condolence letters to family (Box 8)
- Papers and Conferences circa 1952-1972
  - 1952-1960
    - WLS thesis: "Alternative Monetary Interest Theories: A Comparison and Evaluation" 1952 (Box 8)
    - The Federal Reserve Interregional Money Flows Study 1952-1955 (Box 9)
    - "The Effects of Monetary Policy in the First Half of 1953 Southern Economic Association, 1953 (Box 9)
    - "Areas of Regional Research for the Federal Reserve System March 1955 (Box 9)
    - Universities-National Bureau Conference on International Economics April 13-14, 1956 (Box 9)
    - "The Limitations of Monetary Policy" Economic Outlook Conference, University of Michigan 1957 (Box 9)
    - American Statistical Association---Discussion of papers 1958 (Box 9)
    - "Some Unsettled Issues in Monetary Policy," Regional Conference of Duke University March 19-22, 1959 (Box 9)
    - "Debt Management in the United States" January 1960 (Box 9)
    - "Effect of Monetary Policy Upon Our Economy," Joint Economic Committee Testimony February 1960 (Box 9)
    - "Reserve Requirements in the American Monetary System" May 1960 (Box 9)
    - "Marketability, Expectations, and Interest Rate Differentials," University of Chicago, Milton Friedman's Workshop May 20, 1960 (Box 9)
    - "Central Banking Facilities for Nonbank Financial Institutions," Commission on Money and Credit August 1, 1960 (Box 9)
    - Seminar, Federal Reserve Bank of Chicago, on current issues in Monetary Policy September 9, 1960 (Box 9)
  - 1961-1970
    - "Monetary and Fiscal Policy and the Economic Outlook for 1962" Conference on the Economic Outlook November 6, 1961 (Box 9)
    - Philadelphia National Bank-Girard Trust Corn Exchange Bank Merger 1961 (Box 9)
    - Manufacturers-Hanover Trust Case 1961 (Box 9)
    - Brookings Institution Conference on Taxation of Municipal Securities January 1962 (Box 9)
    - White House Conference on National Economic Issues May 21-22, 1962 (Box 9)
    - Miscellaneous papers 1959-1962 (Box 9)
    - Seminar, National Association of Small Business Investment Companies August 29, 1963 (Box 9)
    - "Some Current Issues of United States Economic Policy," American Statistical Association November 19, 1963 (Box 9)
    - Crocker-Anglo National Bank, Citizens National Bank, and Transamerica Corporation Merger Case 1963 (Box 9)
    - Calumet National Bank of Hammond, Indiana and Mercantile National Bank of Hammond, Merger 1963 (Box 9)
    - Seminar, University of Western Ontario March 5, 1964 (Box 9)
    - "Tax Effects of Alternative Monetary Policies on the Tax-Reduction Multiplier, Ohio State University April 30-May 1, 1964 (Box 9)
    - "Program for den Besvch von Wirtschaftswissenschaftlern aus den USA," Berlin, Germany Conference July 1964 (Box 9)
    - Conference of University Professors, Princeton, New Jersey August 29-September 2, 1964 (Box 9)
    - National Industrial Conference Board September 17, 1964 (Box 9)
    - "Emerging Issues in Fiscal Policy" [notes] October 1964 (Box 9)
    - "A Unified Theoretical Framework for Monetary and Fiscal Policy," University of, Illinois May 4, 1965 (Box 9)
    - Conference on Savings and Residential Financing May 6-7, 1965 (Box 9)
    - An Appraisal of Central Bank Policy in the U.S., Columbia University November 22, 1965 (Box 9)
    - Joint Economic Committee 1965 (Box 10)
    - Bank Merger Bills 1965 (Box 10)
    - Committee for Economic Development, Subcommittee on the Federal Reserve and the Structure of Banking 1965-1967 (Box 10)
    - "Time Deposits, Free Reserves, and Monetary Policy," February 2, 1966 (Box 10)
    - "Monetary Versus Fiscal Policy," University of Texas April 21-23, 1966 (Box 10)
    - Conference on Targets and Indicators of Monetary Policy, UCLA April 28, 1966 (Box 10)
    - "Some Reflections of Interest Rates and their Economic Implications" Conference on Savings and Residential Financing May 5-6, 1966 (Box 10)
    - American Economic Association, Panel Discussion May 1966 (Box 10)
    - American-Yugoslav Seminar July 4-9, 1966 (Box 10)
    - "United States Monetary Policy," N.D.E.A. Institute on Economic Education July 27, 1966 (Box 10)
    - "Some Problems of Full Employment," A.E.A. Panel Discussion 1966 (Box 10)
    - Essays on Stabilization Policies, A review of this manuscript for the Brookings Institute 1966-1967 (Box 10)
    - Lectures at colleges and universities 1966-1967 (Box 10)
    - Provident National Bank-Central Penn National Bank of Philadelphia Merger 1966 (Box 10)
    - American Statistical Association Session December 27, 1967 (Box 10)
    - "The Gold Problem and the International Monetary System," Faculty Research Club, University of Michigan April 17, 1968 (Box 10)
    - "The Inflation Problem in Perspective," National Association of Manufacturers September 19, 1968 (Box 10)
    - Lectures at colleges and universities 1968 (Box 10)
    - Special Drawing Rights Amendment Plan 1968 (Box 10)
    - Exchange Rate Flexibility, Council of Economic Advisors 1968, 2 folders (Box 10)
    - Federal Reserve System, Council of Economic Advisers 1968 (Box 10)
    - Council of Economic Advisors, testimony before the Joint Economic Committee January 17, 1969 (Box 11)
    - Statement to Senate Committee on Banking and Currency April 1, 1969 (Box 11)
    - "Some Economic Policy Issues of the Coming Decade," American Statistical Association, New York Chapter April 25, 1969 (Box 11)
    - Social Science Research Council May 1-2, 1969 (Box 11)
    - "A Neo-Keynesian View of Monetary Policy," Federal Reserve Bank of Cleveland June 27, 1969 (Box 11)
    - "The Federal Budget Outlook," Graduate School of Banking, University of Wisconsin August 18, 1969 (Box 11)
    - Northern New England School of Banking, Dartmouth College, New Hampshire September 8, 1969 (Box 11)
    - Conference of University Professors September 9-12, 1969 (Box 11)
    - University Press Club--Panel Discussion, University of Michigan September 26, 1969 (Box 11)
    - "Fiscal Policy and Inflation," JEC Hearing October 13, 1969 (Box 11)
    - Statement to Senate Committee on Labor and Public Welfare December 1, 1969 (Box 11)
    - Econometric Society 1969-1970 (Box 11)
    - Lectures at colleges and universities 1969 (Box 11)
    - Town Meeting Talk, Ann Arbor, Michigan January 31, 1970 (Box 11)
    - Michigan Econometric Society April 3, 1970 (Box 11)
    - Brookings Institution Conference on L. Bach manuscript April 28, 1970 (Box 11)
    - Ditchley Park Conference, Oxfordshire, England June 19-22, 1970 (Box 11)
    - "On Some Current Issues in Monetary Economics, it Western Economic Association Conference August 27-28, 1970 (Box 11)
    - "The Role of Government Intermediaries in the Mortgage Market, Boston Federal Conference October 15-17, 1970 (Box 11)
    - Brookings Institution Panel on Economic Activity 1970 (Box 11)
    - Lectures at colleges and universities 1970 (Box 11)
  - 1971-1972
    - "Assessing the Economic Outlook for 1971 The Implications of the Forecasts," American Statistical Association, Detroit, January 20, 1971 (Box 11)
    - Brookings Institution, Review of S. Chase manuscript February 17, 1971 (Box 11)
    - "On Some Current Issues in Microeconomic Policy, Federal Reserve Bank of New York March 12, 1971 (Box 11)
    - "The Monetorist/Neo-Keynesian Controversy," North Carolina State University March 19, 1971 (Box 11)
    - "Some Aspects of the Keynesian-Monetorist Dispute," Bradley University May 5, 1971 (Box 11)
    - "The New Economic Policy" September 13, 1971 (Box 11)
    - University of Maryland-Five Year Review October 14-15, 1971 (Box 11)
    - Universities--National Bureau Committee for Economic Research 1971 (Box 11)
    - "The Theory of Economic Policy" March 3, 1972 (Box 11)
    - University of Notre Dame, O'Hare Memorial Lecture March 13, 1972 (Box 11)
  - Miscellaneous papers
    - Council of Economic Advisers-Deming Group (Box 11)
    - Usury Ceiling in Michigan (Box 11)
    - Joint Economic Committee (Box 11)
    - Monetary and Fiscal Adjustments for Disarmament (Box 11)
    - Unidentified papers (Box 11)
- Council of Economic Advisors 1961-1969
  - Correspondence 1961-1968 (Box 12)
  - Memoranda
    - 1961-August 1962 (Box 12)
    - September 1962-December 1962 (Box 12)
    - January 1963-March 1963 (Box 12)
    - April 1963-May 1963 (Box 12)
    - June 1963-July 1963 (Box 12)
    - August 1963-September 1963 (Box 12)
    - Undated (Box 12)
  - American Economic Association Meeting 1962 (Box 12)
  - Treasury Consultant's Meeting September 7, 1967 (Box 12)
  - Treasury Consultant's Meeting December 5, 1967 (Box 12)
  - Annual report January 1968 (Box 12)
  - Academic Consultant to Board of Governors, Federal Reserve System April 25, 1968 (Box 12)
  - Treasury Consultants Meeting May 16, 1968 (Box 12)
  - Swearing in as CEA member July 1, 1968 (Box 12)
  - Commission on Mortgage Interest Rates February 11, 1969 (Box 12)
  - Committee for Economic Development (Box 12)
  - Commission on Money and Credit 1959-1961 (Box 12)
  - President Nixon's CEA, speeches by members 1969 (Box 12)
  - Social Science Research Council 1965 (Box 12)
  - U.S. Treasury, Consultants Group (Box 12)
  - Miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 12)
- Committees, conferences, and study groups
  - Committees
    - American Veterans Committee Minutes 1946-1949 (Box 13)
    - Committee on Financial Institutions Papers, 3 folders (Box 13)
    - Graduate Curriculum Committee 1969 (Box 13)
    - LSA Nominating Committee (Box 13)
  - Executive Committees
    - Center for Research on Economic Development (Box 13)
    - Institute of Public Administration (Box 13)
    - Institute for Social Research (Box 13)
  - Conferences
    - American Bankers Association Conferences
      - Purdue University August 29, 1965-September 1, 1965 (Box 13)
      - Princeton University September 16, 1966-September 19, 1966 (Box 13)
    - Budget Conference, Brookings Institute July 31, 1967-August 1, 1967 (Box 13)
  - Study Groups
    - Federal Reserve Discount Rate Study (Box 13)
    - Savings and Loan Industry study (Box 13)
    - Social Science Research Council
      - Monetary Policy Study Group (Box 13)
      - Study of the Monetary Mechanism, 3 folders (Box 13)